Marc-Aurèle RIVIÈRE

Research / Data Scientist

Cognitive & Data Scientist & Specialized in behavioral research and multimodal HMI & Currently working as a research engineer designing, developing, and evaluating assistive devices for the blind, within AR environments & Proficient R programmer.

Work experience

Research Engineer

LITIS Rouen, France / 2021

- ♦ Design & develop a VR/AR platform in Unity to evaluate and train non-visual navigation for Visually Impaired People (VIP). Navigation-relevant information is collected using motion tracking systems and provided to the user through custom audio-tactile wearable interfaces.
- ♦ Evaluate the impact of the information provided on navigational performance.

Graduate Teaching Fellow

University of Rouen Rouen, France / 2017 - 2020

Gave lectures & practicals on Web Development, Python programming, GUI design in Java (Swing), Image Processing in Python, and Intro to ML/DL models for Computer Vision

Engineering Internship

SKERI San Francisco / 2018 - 2019

Worked on an indoor localization solution using Visual Inertial Odometry, particle filtering, object detection, and real-time video streaming (Python/Flask, Swift)

Research Internship

LPNC & GIPSA-Lab Grenoble, France / 2016

- ♦ Developed an audio interface converting depth images into sound (C++/Qt)
- ♦ Evaluated audio-feedback based shape recognition in blindfolded participants

Education

PhD - Cognitive Neurosciences (unfinished - COVID)

Normandy University Rouen, France / 2017 - 2020

Design, implement, and evaluate a wearable haptic interface to help Visually Impaired People navigate autonomously, based on spatial cognition & perception models

Student Entrepreneurship program

PEPITE Rouen, France / 2018 - 2019

Project management, KPI, Business plan, Branding, IP, A/B testing

MSc. - Cognitive Neurosciences

PHELMA - Grenoble INP Grenoble, France / 2015 - 2016

Bayesian modeling ♦ Vision, Attention, Language, and Memory models ♦ Deep Learning

MSc. - Social & Organisational Psychology

University of Strasbourg Strasbourg, France / 2013 - 2015

Recruitment, Skill assessment, Occupational Health, Work Ergonomics

R&D projects

ACCESSPACE project

- ♦ Designed a wearable vibrotactile belt for haptic-based navigation for VIP
- \blacklozenge Developed wearable camera-based solutions for indoor localization and mapping

TETMOST & NAV-VIR projects

- ♦ Participated in the design of an interactive haptic tablet to display simplified images
- ♦ Developed an application to display images and maps through this tablet (Java/Arduino)

Data Science projects

LT-AoP project

- ♦ Processed and analyzed immunohistochemistry data with generalized multilevel models
- ◆ Automated technical reports & documentation generation for those analyses (accessible here)

DE-AoP project

- ♦ Processed and analyzed RT-qPCR data using multilevel models
- ◆ Created an interactive web application (Shiny) to facilitate data exploration for team members



- marc.aurele.riviere@gmail.com
- France
- 32 years old
- % https://ma-riviere.me

Languages

French - Native

English - Bilingual

Spanish - A2

Norwegian - A2

Assets

Inquisitive | Autonomous | Assertive | Creative | Adaptable

Training & Courses

- ♦ Cognitive Modeling (CMAH'21)
- ♦ Data Science School (<u>DS3'21</u>)
- ♦ Neuromatch Academy (NMA'20)
- ◆ Probabilistic Al School (<u>ProbAl'19</u>)
 ◆ Computer Vision School (ICVSS'17)
- **Conference Talks**
- ♦ RUNN 2019 (Caen, FR)
- ♦ CJCSC 2019 (Paris, FR)
- ♦ ICCHP 2018 (Linz, Austria)
- ♦ HANDICAP 2018 (Paris, FR)

Conference Posters

- ♦ NER 2019 (San Francisco, USA)
- ♦ RUNN 2019 (Caen, FR)
- ♦ CRD 2019 (Caen, FR)
- ♦ French-Polish Research & Innovation forum 2017 (Warsaw, PO)

Invited Talks

- ♦ Burgundy University (Dijon, FR)
- ♦ Politechnika Łódzka (Łódź, PL)
- ♦ SKERI (San Francisco, USA)
- ◆ French-Norwegian PhD Day (Trondheim, NO)

Technical skills

Data Science

Data wrangling (Tidyverse, data.table) ♦ Database (DuckDB, PostgreSQL) ♦ Web Scraping (rvest, httr2) ♦ Visualizations (ggplot) ♦ Dashbords (Shiny) ♦ Publishing (Quarto, R Markdown)

Statistics & Machine Learning

Bayesian Generalized Multilevel Location-Scale-Shape models ♦ Generalized Additive Models ♦ Survival Analysis ♦ IRT ♦ ARIMA ♦ HMM ♦ Mixtures ♦ Power Analysis

Web Development

JAM-Stack (Quarto, Hugo) & Back-End (NodeJS, Flask, plumber) & Shiny & Flutter

Computer Vision & Robotics

Image Processing ♦ Feature detection ♦ Segmentation ♦ Odometry ♦ SLAM

Transferable skills

Behavioral Research

- ♦ Behavioral experiments (Psychophysics, Eye-tracking, Motion-tracking, VR/AR)
- ♦ Statistical & Computational modeling

Scientific Communication

- ♦ Co-organized the IHAW'20 international conference (canceled due to COVID)
- ♦ Organized a University-funded 2-day conference for PhD Students (JED 2017)
- ♦ Initiated & participated in several international collaborations (USA, Italy, Poland)
- ♦ Engaged in several public dissemination events (in exhibits & schools, or in the press)

R&D Project Management

- ♦ Created & wrote a 600k€ research grant proposal (ANR project "SAM-Guide", 2021)
- ◆ Participated in ethics applications & Data Management Plan (GDPR)
- ♦ Recruited & supervised multiple interns from various fields

Publications (journal)

Rodriguez-Duboc, A., Basille-Duguay, M., Debonne, A., **Rivière**, **M.-A.**, Vaudry, D., & Burel, D. (In Press). Apnea of Prematurity induces short and long-term development-related transcriptional changes in the murine cerebellum. *Molecular and Cellular Neuroscience*.

Faugloire, E., Lejeune, L., **Rivière**, **M.-A.**, & Mantel, B. (2022). Spatiotemporal influences on the recognition of two-dimensional vibrotactile patterns on the abdomen. *Journal of Experimental Psychology: Applied*, *28*(3), 606–628. https://doi.org/10.1037/xap0000404

Publications (proceedings)

Coughlan, J.M., Biggs, B., **Rivière**, **M-A.**, Shen, H. (2020). An Audio-Based 3D Spatial Guidance AR System for Blind Users. In Miesenberger, K., Manduchi, R., Covarrubias Rodriguez, M., Peňáz, P. (Eds.), *Lecture Notes in Computer Science* (Vol. 12376, pp. 475–484). Springer Int. Publishing. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-030-58796-3 55

Riviere, M-A., Gay, S., Romeo, K., Pissaloux, E., Bujacz, M., Skulimowski, P., & Strumillo, P. (2019). NAV-VIR: An audio-tactile virtual environment to assist visually impaired people. *Proceedings of the 9th International IEEE/EMBS Conference on Neural Engineering*, 1038–1041. https://doi.org/10.1109/NER.2019.8717086

Riviere, M-A., Gay, S., Pissaloux, E. (2018). TactiBelt: Integrating Spatial Cognition and Mobility Theories into the Design of a Novel Orientation and Mobility Assistive Device for the Blind. In Miesenberger, K., Kouroupetroglou, G. (Eds.), *Lecture Notes in Computer Science* (Vol. 10897, pp. 110–113). Springer Int. Publishing. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-94274-2 16

Gay, S., **Rivière**, **M-A.**, Pissaloux, E. (2018). Towards Haptic Surface Devices with Force Feedback for Visually Impaired People. In Miesenberger, K., Kouroupetroglou, G. (Eds.), *Lecture Notes in Computer Science* (Vol. 10897, pp. 258–266). Springer Int. Publishing. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-94274-2 36

Programming Skills

R

Tidyverse, data.table, arrow, brms, *Stanverse*, glmmTMB, afex, mgcv, *Easystats*, emmeans, ggplot, gt

Python

skimage, Tidypolars, OpenCV, flask, plotnine

Java

Swing, JAXB

C#

Unity, LINQ

JavaScript

NodeJS, Socket.io, Arquero; OJS

HTML & CSS

Bootstrap

SQL

DuckDB, PostgreSQL

Stan

C / C++

Frameworks & Tools

Scientific Publishing

Quarto, R Markdown, LaTeX

Git / SVN

Shiny

Unity

OpenMaze, Steam Audio

OpenCV

Flutter

Arduino

SPSS

IDE

- ♦ RStudio, VS Code, PyCharm, IntelliJ
- ♦ Unity Editor, Android Studio
- ♦ G. Colab, Jupyter, RStudio Cloud